Guide to the Canvass White Papers, 1814-1835
White, Canvass Papers
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Canvass White Papers, 1814-1835
609
White, Canvass, 1790-1834
.9 cubic ft.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Papers documenting canal engineer and cement manufacturer Canvass White's career.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Canal engineer and cement manufacturer of Whitestown, Oneida County, N.Y.
Canvass White served in the War of 1812, made surveys on the Erie Canal, visited England to study canals, introduced hydraulic cement into the United States, manufactured cement, was president of the Cohoes Company, chief engineer of the Delaware Breakwater, the Delaware and Rariton Canal, the Enfield Falls Canal, the Louisville & Portland Canal, the Union Canal, and consulting engineer for the Chambly Canal, the Chesapeake & Ohio Canal, the New York Waterworks, the Portsmouth & Lancaster Railroad, for improvements on the Union Canal, and for other engineering projects.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Correspondence, legal and business papers and other papers relating to White's service in the War of 1812, his engineering activities, and his cement manufacturing business with his brother Hugh at Chittenango, N.Y.
Includes material relating to the Camden and Amboy Railroad and Transportation Company, Chambly Canal, Champlain Canal, Chesapeake and Ohio Canal, Cohoes company, Delaware and Rariton Canal, Delaware Breakwater, Enfield Falls Canal, Erie Canal, Croton Aqueduct, Louisville and Portland Canal, Mohawk River, Pennsylvania Canal, Union Canal, and Utica and Schenectady Railroad. Correspondents include Major Bender, Edwin A. Douglass, General Jessup, William Lehman, George Olmsted, William Read, Peter Remsen, Alfred Smith, and Joseph Trumball.
Administrative Information
Container List
- Link to a PDF finding aid.
  All the material in the collection may not be covered by this guide.
- Series I. Correspondence
  Contents of folders include letters, inventories, contracts, financial records, reports, map, ticket, steel engraving, advertising, acts, pamphlet, specifications
  - 1814 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1815 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1817-1820 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1820-March 1824 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - April-December 1824 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 1825 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 1826 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - January-April 1827 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - May-August 1827 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - September-December 1827-1828 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - January-April 1828 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - May-December 1828, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 1829 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - January-March 1830 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - May-July 1830 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - August 1830 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - September-November 1830 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - December 1830, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - 1830-1832 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Added January 4, 1950 from Hugh White Papers
  - January-February 1831 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - March-April 1831 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - May-August 1831 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - September-December 1831 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - January 1832 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - February-April 1832 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - May-June 1832 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - July 1832 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - August 1832 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - September 1832 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - October 1832 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - November 1832 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - December 1832 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - January 1833 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - February 1833 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - March 1833 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - April 1833 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - May 1833 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - June 1833 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - July 1833 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - August-September 1833 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - October 1833 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - November-December 1833 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - 1833 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - New York History journal, Article "New York's Early Engineers", July 1945 (Box 3)
  - January-April 1834 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - May-August 1834 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - September-December 1834 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - 1835 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - 1836 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Undated (Box 3, Folder 6-7)
  - Cement, Undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Chambly Canal, Undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
    Estimates, letter
  - Croton Aqueduct, Undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Delaware and Raritan Canal Co., Undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Enfield Fall Canal, Undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence (List 1), 1827-1836; Undated (Box 4, Folder 1-4)
  - Correspondence: Heigh and Canvass White letters (not listed), 1824-1847 (Box 4, Folder 5-8)
- Series II. Drawings
  - Plans for bridges, locks, dams etc., Undated (Box 3, Folder 13-14)